Final Fantasy VI - Ted Woolsey Uncensored Edition 
Bug Fixes and Patches Used Compendium by Rodimus Primal
---------------------------------------------------------------------------

This document is designed to go into detail about what bug fixes were used
in the making of Final Fantasy VI - Ted Woolsey Uncensored Edition. The 
reason for this is becaused the original vanilla game was riddled with
bugs, glitches, and other various issues that the ROM Hacking community
has went out of their way to fix. While not every single bugfix available
was used, the ones chosen were used because 1) they were issues needed to
be fixed, 2) They don't alter the feel of the original, and 3) they were 
comaptible overall when working together. This means that exploits, like 
Vanish/Doom, and funny glitches, like Psycho Cyan, are not in this project.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------

Base patch, Final Fantasy VI - Ted Woolsed Uncensored Edition -

If you just use the base patch, all of this work was done to the original
SNES game. All versions include them. These are the patches used and all of
the work done under the hood:

-Monster, Esper, and Town Graphics Restoration- Using the various ROM hacking 
tools at my disposal, I restored all of the monster sprites, the Siren Esper,
and the Pub signs (they were called Cafe in the US) as an initial uncensoring
of the game. In addition, the Silence spell graphic was called Mute in the US.
Instead of using the Japanese graphic, I changed the lettering from Mute to
say Silence. The only bit of uncensoring that I was not able to do was the 
graphics for the final battle (see below).

-Final Battle Tiers Graphics (Dr. Meat) - I was unsuccessful in doing this 
myself. However, Dr. Meat was kind enough to share his work to add to this
project. The graphics are now uncensored. 

-Final Fantasy VI Titlescreen Mod (Yazoo) - This restores the title screen
from the US Final Fantasy III, back to Final Fantasy VI.

-B Button Dash (C) (Master ZED) - This adds the ability to hold the B Button down
to dash while in towns and dungeons. The Sprint Shoes, when equipped, will now
allow for double the speed when the B Button is pressed down, just like it is
on the Playstation version of the game.
Take note that this has been altered to act as a Cancel Button Dash, meaning
that it is now compatible with the button settings configuration. 

-Sliding Dash (SilentEnigma) - An issue with the updated Dash function causes the
sprites to appear like they are standing still when running at full speed
(Dash + Sprint Shoes). This corrects that behavior to make the animations run
smoothly once again. 

-Restore Ability Names (by angelo26) - This allowed expansion for the magic spell
names used in the game. As such, almost all spells now used the modern naming 
used by Final Fantasy games. So Ice is now Blizzard, etc. This also added in
the Class Names to all characters. Some of the names in this patch had to be
modified as they do not match current releases of the game. 

-Extended item descriptions (Dr Meat) - The original game was limited in the 
amount of space it had for item descriptions. Using a little ingenuiety, Dr Meat 
expanded that space, allowing for full modern descriptions for all items in the 
game.

-Gogo Yellow Streak (assassin17) - Minor graphical glitch on Gogo's portrait 
in the game menu on a vanilla US Final Fantasy III (not in the Japanese version). 
This fixes that issue.

-Esper Battle Menu MP Fix (Lenophis) - A US version created bug, "MP" doesn't 
show up when you press up in the magic menu to Summon your equipped Esper. 
This is now fixed.

-Tritoch Graphical Fix (bydoless) - Summoning the Esper, Valigarmanda (Tritoch 
in vanilla FFIII), has a piece of it's tail missing when the spell is cast. 
This restores that.

-Auction Chocobo Fix (Madsiur) - The Chocobo seen in the Auction House in 
Jidoor has a graphical glitch that sees it's face slightly cut off by one of the 
girls on stage. This fixes that issue.

-Inconsistent Gungho dialogue fix (assassin17) - When first meeting Gungho in 
Thamasa in the WOB, there are two conversations that can take place: one without 
Strago in your party, and one with. There's a line of dialogue from Gungho in both 
versions where he addresses Strago in the second person, that doesn't make sense 
when Strago's absent.  There's also a seemingly extra line of dialogue in the 
Strago-present version, where Gungho inexplicably speaks of him in the third person. 
This is now fixed to make the chats make far more sense.

-Gerard and Sabin (Leet Sketcher) - There is a line of dialogue in the game that 
would have been appropriate when Celes (and Sabin, if you picked him up in Tzen) meet 
up with Edgar, aka "Gerad", in Nikeah. The line conveys Sabin's surprise to discover 
his brother's masquerade, which makes perfect sense, but for some reason the line was 
dummied out. Although this isn't actually a bug, this inserts the line back in.

-Sketch Glitch bugfix (assassin17) - The most game breaking bug (it can corrupt your
save files!) is one that even Square themselves fixed in a Version 1.1 to the US 
release of Final Fantasy III. Since TWUE is based on 1.0, this fixes that bug,
ensuring that you won't run into data corruption when using the Sketch command.

-RMOVE to REMOVE (Gi Nattak) - In the Equipment Menu in Vanilla Final Fantasy III,
the choices are EQUIP OPTIMUM RMOVE EMPTY. Apparently, most people overlooked the
fact that Remove was missing an E for spacing purposes, at least until I decapped
the letters in TWUE. The folks who made Pandora's Box changed it EMPTY to NONE in
their project. Gi Nattak was able to make a solitary patch for this, which is now
added to TWUE, but the letters are not captilized. So now, the Equipment Menu reads
like this: Equip Optimum Remove None. 

-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------

Patches used in the "with Bug Fixes" versions:

This list is quite long due to the sheer number of bugs present in Final Fantasy VI.
Again, not every bugfix out there was used, however I believe that they belong in the
game as a majority of them have been implemented in later releases of the game.

-Upgrades not Downgrades - Some Espers were tweaked so that their use made sense. Raiden, 
which is supposed to be an upgrade to Odin, gives a Strength +2 bonus at level up. Later
releases of the game changed this to Speed +2. This was done here as well, which gives
players incentive to get the upgrade. In addition, Ramuh now teaches Thundara at a rate 
of X3 and Ifrit teaches Drain at X3.

-Elemental Display (Lenophis) - Originally, when checking an item’s properties, looking 
at the elemental aspect will only display up to 6 elements. There was no bias of any one
element taking precedence, it just capped itself at 6. That was because of how the screen
was arranged. Now, the screen is arranged to now allow up to 8 elements display for any 
property.

-Border Crossing (Imzogelmo, Lenophis, Novalia Spirit) - On an overworld map, battles are 
determined by choosing a formation from a group within 32×32 tile zone. The game calculates 
the zone based on the coordinates of the party. However, the zone calculation is not run on 
each step, but rather on each redraw of the map. Examples of redraws include exiting battle, 
exiting the menu, and exiting a town. It is easy to see this bug by entering and exiting the 
menu at a boundary where the enemy formations change, then walking into the adjacent zone 
until a battle is triggered. Monsters will appear from the previous zone. Now the behavior
is corrected by loading from variables that are updated with each step. 

-Homesick Gau (Djibriel) - Gau, when returning from a Leap, needs a monster slot to occupy.
This slot is always designed as the sixth slot (i.e. the last one).  Obviously, monster 
formations of six monsters will not allow Gau to return.  However, there is also a great amount
of monster formations which have plenty room for Gau, yet have a monster in the sixth slot 
anyway, preventing Gau from returning while he normally could.  Over 40 monster formations 
which appear on the Veldt have been optimized, and Gau can now return from any monster 
formations, passing the usual criteria, as long as it isn't a team of six.

-255 Hours Display (Leviathan Mist) - While not really a bugfix, this raises the number of
hours the can keep track off. The timer now maxes at 255:59 instead of 99:59.

-For What Ails Ya! (Imzogelmo, Lenophis, Novalia Spirit) - When using an item, there are 
circumstances that can surface that would cause you to lose it, even though you never used it.
In a non-hacked game, this only matters when a character dies and gets revived. In hacked games,
when the "don't deplete from inventory" flag for items can get used, it can be more of a
factor, since the items may just randomly disappear. The game supports it, but at times it seems 
to forget or something overwrites it. When any command can write to the a character's reserve, 
calls are now added to update inventory if there is an item in the reserve.

-Bad Decoration (Lenophis) - Summoning the Esper Crusader will make the reflect barrier look funny. 
Less "ha ha" funny, more "ew" funny. Beyond that, you can only notice it if you and a monster 
survive the summoning. Now Reflect barriers will be blue and not brown when Summoning Crusader.

-I condemn thee to hell! (Lenophis) - Any monster that starts with the condemn status will not 
die from it, because the timer is never set when battles start. Now the timer will start and 
can kill the monster if the timer runs out. 

-Suplex wrongfully splits damage fix (assassin17) - The Suplex/Meteor Strike/Meteor Suplex Blitz
only attacks one monster, but splits the damage as if it was attacking more than one target. This
corrects it so using this Blitz will damage a monster like it should.

-Allo Ver (Death Warden) Fix (Master ZED) - The Death Warden (Allo Ver in FFIII) should be in a 
monster formation to allow it to show up on the Veldt. This corrects this oversight and now 
this monster can appear on the Veldt, and the Rage can be learned. This is superceded by the
following patch.

-Rage Restoration patch (Terii Senshi) - In addition to the Death Warden, you can now also learn
Typhon and Siegfried on the Veldt. 

-Step Mine (Traveler) missing digit fix (assassin17) - Fixes a missing digit in the MP cost of the
Traveler Lore so that it is correctly displayed.

-Some MP changes don't update menus fix (assassin17) - If a character doesn't have enought MP to
cast a spell, a variety of issues can occur. This fixes that oversight so weapons and spells
are not incorrectly affected by this.

-Pink Gogo bugfix (Imzogelmo) - In Cyan's dream, if Gogo is in your party, he will be incorrectly
colored pink  when you see him frozen. This gives him the correct color.

-Reflect barrier shown on bodyguards fix (assassin17) - When using the Zantetsuken (Scimitar in the
US FFIII) or any one hit kill weapons are used on targets with blocks like Knights Code, a reflect
barrier is shown instead of an X animation. This corrects that behavior.

-Running Popsicle / Lead-footed Esper fix (assassin17) - When you try to run in battle, a Morphed 
Terra isn't illustrated as running, even though she's fully capable of doing so (and will briefly be 
shown striding when she finally escapes).  Meanwhile, a Frozen character will be given a running 
animation, even though they're unable to flee. This purely graphical bug happens because when the 
game prevents Zombied, Petrified, Dead, Sleeping, and Stopped characters from getting a run animation,
it oddly counts Morphed characters as among those ineligible, but not Frozen ones. This corrects this
so Frozen characters won't move and Esper Terra will when running.

-Mine Cart Fix (Imzogelmo) - Fixes an issue with certain Mag Roaders battles on the Mine Cart where
it incorrectly randomizes the battles.

-Deceptive Tapir (assassin17) - Tapir, summoned by Mog's Dance, heals any ailment besides Freeze or 
those that can't be healed normally (such as Charm).  On top of that, its special effect will fully 
restore the HP and MP of sleeping targets.  When the special effect detects that a target isn't 
sleeping, it will trigger a "Miss" message, which is misleading because the status ailments are 
still removed from the target. This fix causes the Tapir special effect function to essentially do 
nothing for awake targets.  No "Miss" message appears; their ailments are simply cured.  This does 
NOT influence the unnamed tapir that appears automatically to wake up snoozers, as that's not even 
the same spell.  

-Evade Bug Fix (Terii Senshi) - Incorrect coding caused the Evade stat to do nothing, but instead
be calculatd by MBlock. Because of this, it is harder to dodge physical attacks and blind status
becomes moot. This corrects this so that it properly uses the Evade Stat. 

-Rippler Bug Fix (Terii Senshi) - Rippler is a lore that swaps status of the target and attacker.
Due to a bug, it also swaps use of Interceptor (Shadow's Dog), Terra's Morph, and Gau's Rage. This
means you can LOSE use of Interceptor PERMANENTLY. Now, Rippler will only swap the statuses it
is suppossed to.

-FC 05 Bug Fix (Master ZED) - Corrects the behavior of when an enemy should counterattack, which 
depends on if the damage is to HP or MP.

-Invisible Chests on Phantom Train fix (Shaded Magus) - Some treasue chests on the Phantom Train
are invisible and should not be. This fixes them so that they are visible. 

-Frozen Terra Fix (Madsiur) - If one of your characters is dead, and you say No to Banon 3 times,
one of your dead characters might end up blocking your path, essentially causing you to not be
able to proceed with the game. This fixes that error so that the game will not be frozen.

-Jump/Launcher and Jump/Super Ball fix (assassin17) - Normally, if an enemy uses Launcher when all 
the characters have jumped, or a character uses Super Ball when all the enemies have jumped, the 
battle will bug out.  Targets will be invisible; actions will be prevented; it's a mess (though it's 
largely remedied if another Super Ball or Launcher is used with actual targets present).  This fix 
prevents all the misbehavior by making sure the function that deals with Launcher and Super Ball 
always clears a counter variable, even when no targets are found.

-Pincer+Row Bugfix (assassin17) - Normally, when you begin a fight in a Pincer attack, all characters 
are in the front row.  You can use the Row command to [randomly] turn around, but oddly it also 
switches rows.  This isn't a visible change, but something you'll notice in damage dealt and received.  
Since there should be no rows for characters in a Pincer (and for enemies, no rows in a Side attack, 
but they don't change rows mid-battle anyway), the effect on damage becomes a very sneaky bug. This fix 
stops the Row command and the R.Polarity spell from switching a character's row when they are caught in 
a Pincer, unless all the enemies on one side are gone.  

-Jump Megafix A - (assassin17) - Patch A used for compatibility with other patches. There are five major
bugs with the breakable sword, Organyx (Ogre Nix in FFIII) and the Jump command. This corrects all 5 of
them so that the weapon will work as intended.

-Miscolored Command Names - Gear Based - (assassin17) - Gear based version for compatibility. This fix
ensures that Gogo's command list is colored correctly based on what equipment he is wearing. 

-Recapture the Glory (assassin17) - When using the Capture command, some weapons do not use their 
special properties, resulting in only use of a Steal attempt. This fixes the error so that the weapons
will use their effect in addition to the Steal attempt. 

-Bridge Correction (Mike Farrell) - A minor graphical error on the bridge to the Sealed Gate during battle
is corrected so that the wrong tile displays correctly.

-Wrong Way, Idiot! (Mike Farrell) - When entering the town of Thamasa, sometimes you are facing down instead
of up. This small fix now has you facing the right direction. 

-Banon Riding (Leet Sketcher) - Banon does not have a riding a Chocobo sprite, and if you attempt to do so,
moments of Esper Terra will show up instead of Banon. This corrects this by adding sprites for Banon 
while riding a Chocobo. 

-Backwards Jump (Leet Sketcher) - In battle, you can attempt to flee by holding down L and R simultaneously. 
If one of your party members attempts to Jump while running, they will appear to be doing just that - 
Jumping and running away at the same time. This fix allows that party member to focus solely on Jumping.

-Bird Bars (Leet Sketcher) - If Setzer gets three BARs on Slots, he will Summon a random Esper. If that 
Esper is Phoenix, he will take an extra step forward before Summoning it. If the Esper is Quetzalli, he 
will land too far backwards from his subsequent Jump. In either case, Setzer is now removed from the 
line-up, either too far forward or too far backward. This fix ensures he stays in line in both cases.

-Castle Party (Leet Sketcher) - During the scene where Sabin infiltrates the Imperial Camp near Doma 
Castle, the game repeatedly switches back and forth between him in the camp and Cyan in Doma. As the 
game switches back from Cyan to Sabin, sometimes the game changes the order of the members of Sabin's 
party. This is especially poignant if Shadow is in Sabin's party. This fix ensures that the order of
all members in both parties is always maintained.

-Chain of Command - Gear Based (Leet Sketcher) - Gear Based to ensure compatibility. If any party 
member equips certain Relics, their commands will change; for example, the Heiji Jitte Relic changes 
"Slot" to "Gil Toss". If Gogo equips one of these Relics, that command will be replaced everywhere 
except in the command selection screen under his Status menu. This fix eliminates this oversight.

-False Knight (Leet Sketcher) - Party members wearing the Knights Code relic can guard their 
Near Fatal allies from incoming physical attacks. If the attack misses, when they return to the line-up,
they may be incorrectly be shown over the next party member or under the previous party member in the 
line-up. This fix ensures that party members don't clip over each other.

-Imp's Rage (Leet Sketcher) - If Gau tries to Rage while he's an Imp, be it through player choice or 
autonomy, he'll Attack instead because Rage is not allowed in Imp status. He also will not have any 
of the statuses that come with the Rage; however, he will still be autonomous. The same goes for Dance:
if Mog tries to Dance as an Imp, he'll Attack instead, but will still be autonomous. This fix prevents 
autonomy from both commands if the character is an Imp.

-Imp's Call (Leet Sketcher) - The Imp status forbids you from attempting most commands; if they are 
already in progress, it replaces them with Attasck. If the replaced command was an attempt to summon 
an Esper, which you're only allowed to do once per battle, you lose the ability to summon it after 
returning to normal. This fix prevents Imp status from taking away your ability to Summon after you 
remove it.

-Imp Skimp (Leet Sketcher) - Monsters can receive Imp status in battle; if they do, their sprite is 
changed to an Imp. However, this is not an automatic process, and in fact the only way to change the 
sprite to or from an Imp is via the Imp spell. Any other Imp-inflicting spell, such as Rippler, will 
not cause any change. Worse, the Imp spell ALWAYS changes the sprite as long as Imp hits, regardless 
of whether or not the monster actually received the status. This fixes Imp sprites to be displayed 
automatically, and also fixes a bug regarding Celes: if she absorbs the Imp spell using Runic, she will 
change into an Imp, then abruptly change back.

-Item/Magic Counter (Leet Sketcher) - Certain enemies such as K.Behemoth and FlameEater have scripts 
that involve countering against certain spells used against them. However, if this does indeed happen, 
they will subsequently counter any attack against them until another spell is used. This fix ensures 
that those enemies only counter the specified spells.

-Lens Cap (Leet Sketcher) - When you meet the White Dragon in the Fanatics' Tower, the camera centers 
itself on you before the fight starts. However, it will not move back unless you exit and re-enter the
 room. This fix makes sure the camera stays in place.

-Magitek Madness (Leet Sketcher) - If Doom is cast on a target, that target's soul will be whisked away 
by the Grim Reaper. If Doom is cast on a party member in Magitek Armor, their soul will have no legs. 
This fix ensures that legs are included.

-Morph Mayhem (Leet Sketcher) - There are two bugs associated with Terra's Morph ability. First, the 
gauge is allowed to continue running while Terra is asleep, Stopped, Frozen, or while someone else is 
using Quick. If it expires during this time, Terra will not automatically Revert as she is supposed to. 
Second, if Terra leaves the battle for any reason, including fleeing or being Sneezed out, the gauge will 
continue to run down. This fix pauses the gauge in the Stop and Quick cases, re-queues Revert in the 
Sleep and Frozen cases, and removes Morph in the other cases.

-Phoenix Chest (Leet Sketcher) - After you find Locke in the Phoenix Cave and he's opened the chest 
containing the Phoenix Magicite, you can return to the Phoenix Cave later to discover that the chest has 
mysteriously been reclosed permanently. Since it cannot be opened again, the likely intent was for the chest 
to stay open, so this is now fixed.

-Ultimate Damage (Leet Sketcher) - There are two major problems with the game's damage algorithm.  First, 
it is possible for the calculated damage to reach numbers outside the 16-bit range, resulting in an overflow. 
This can result in a character that would normally deal over 65,000 damage, instead dealing hardly any damage 
at all. The second is that the Genji Glove and Offering Relics, which are supposed to reduce damage from weapons,
instead reduce ALL physical damage. This fixes both of those issues simultaneously.

-Unequipium (Leet Sketcher) - When event scripts such as the "Unequip some party members?" guy remove equipment
from characters not in your party, the game neglects to reload their information based on their now-empty 
equipment. As such, if you proceed to change your party members afterwards, some characters may have 
improperly-displayed HP or MP values. This fix ensures that the game recalculates stats after removing equipment.

-Vanish/Runic (Leet Sketcher) - If Celes or Gogo absorbs the Vanish spell using Runic, they will not gain the 
Vanish status, but they will still disappear only to reappear immediately. This fix removes all disappearing 
and reappearing in this scenario.

-Zombie/Tapir A (Leet Sketcher) - The spell Tapir is used to heal negative statuses on your party and is 
accessible through Mog's Dance. However, one of the statuses it heals is Zombie, which would leave you 
with a living, healthy character with 0 HP. This fix makes Tapir heal a small amount of HP when it 
cures Zombie status. Fix A has been applied and will heal 1/8 of the target's HP.

-Zombie/Rippler A (Leet Sketcher) - The Rippler Lore is unique. It swaps all of the statuses between the 
caster and the target. A known flaw in Rippler is that is swaps several "invisible" statuses, including 
Morph and Dog Block. There exists a patch written by Terii Senshi that fixes this; however, it fails to
address a specific issue. A problem Terii Senshi's patch fails to address occurs when a Zombified character
is affected by Rippler. If Rippler causes that character to lose their Zombie status, they will still have 
0 HP as per the Zombie status...but they will be alive. This is one of a few ways a character can be alive 
despite having 0 HP. Fix A is applied, the entity that loses Zombie status will be healed by an amount of 
HP equal to the HP of the entity on the other end of Rippler.

-Description Disruption 1.2 (Silent Enigma) This patch addresses a minor text display bug in the field menu’s
item section. Normally, if the player enters an item’s details screen (elemental affinity / applicable characters)
before the item’s description text has finished filling the upper panel, the text stream gets cut off partway.
This bugfix ensures that an item’s description continues filling the upper panel uninterrupted, even after entering
the item details screen. 

-Allergic Dog Fix (Novalia Spirit) - Like the Rippler bug, equipping Shadow with a Cherub Down (Angel Wings
in TWUE), which bestows Float status, will deprive him of his use of Interceptor. This fix corrects that
behavior. 

------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------


Patches used on the "With Add-Ons" patches:

In addition to ALL of the bugfixes listed above, the "With Add-Ons" patches also include some fantastic 
tweaks that, in all honesty, should have been the norm when the game first came out. In fact, one of them
is actually on all modern releases of the game.

-Blitz Screen (Leet Sketcher) - This adds the names of the Blitz attacks above the input commmands on the
Blitz menu. Since this is something modern versions of the game now include, it was a no-brainer. Note,
the names seen in battle are longer due to the "Restored Abilities" patch. Some names are abbreviated in
the menu. For example, in battle, the game will display "Rising Phoenix." However in menu, it will display
it as "RisingPhnx" for short.

-Y Equip Relics (Leet Sketcher)- With this, you can now switch between the equiping a characters weapons 
and armor screen with equiping their Relics screen just by pressing Y. It makes switching things out much 
easier, instead of having to back fully out to the Main Menu. 

-Rewards Display (Hatzen08) - This modifies the item list when selecting an item in the Colosseum. Instead of
displaying how many are in your inventory, this will display what your reward is for winning. This makes
going to the Colosseum more engaging as you can now choose the right item for the right reward.

-Mini-Maps Upgrade (Madsiur) - This gives a graphical improvement to the Mini-Map in game so that separation
of walkable land and mountains are now visible. This makes navigating terrain on the world map MUCH easier.

-Rage Checklist Main 2 (Novalia Spirit) - This patch generates a more comprehensive list of Rages in the main 
menu. In addition to providing the standard information, the list will also indicate, in a gray color, what 
Rages could currently be learned by returning to the Veldt with Gau.

-Rage and Dance Description Expansion (SilentEnigma) - This expands descriptions to include Dances and Rages.
The Dance descriptions translations are taken from the GBA version of the game, with tweaks made so that
they fit into the description box. Rages now allow for players to know what each Rage will do when used 
in battle. 

-Bushido Speed-Up - A simple change in how fast it takes Cyan's Bushido meter to fill when used in battle. 
This will make using him much less of a chore when wanting to use his special skills.   

-------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------

If you've read this far, you're probably thinking to yourself, "WOW what a long list! What patch do I use?"
Or you might be so overwhelmed by the amount of bugfixes that you might want to just use the base patch.
While the choice is yours, it's HIGHLY recommended that you use the "+Bug Fixes, Updated Opera, & Add-Ons" 
patch. The Bug fixes used are worth having properly fixed, the updated Opera matches the Music better, and 
the Add-Ons are like icing to a cake so many of us love! Enjoy! 



