Additional patches that can be added to Final Fantasy VI Ted Woolsey Uncensored Edition - 

Thanks to Chronosplit of RHDN, a lot of testing has been done for the mass amount of bugfixes 
and additional add-ons that have been out there in addition to the bugfixes that are already
present in all versions of this hack. Instead of going throught every single one of them and
adding them to the already existing bugfix patches, Chronosplit has compiled a list of all 
the patches that are and are not compatible with Ted Woolsey Uncensored Edition. Remember,
adding any of them is completely optional and if you don't want to add it to your personal
version of Woolsey Uncensored that is up to you, the user. Also, the new add-ons patch has
custom code to add the Music Player and may interfere with any additional bugfixes. 

Patching Order:
1. TWUE with Bugfixes (Opera optional.)
2. Add a header.

3. First to get these out of the way:
-Vanish/Doom Fix
-Psycho Cyan Fix
-Stuck in a Pose

4. Assassin17/MasterZED:
All bugfixes seem to check out except:
-What's already in the patch 
-Magic overflow, present in a later patch.
-Multiple options used (Though there shouldn't be any difference in results, 
 it's your choice which one to use.  These are merely suggestions):  
 Simple Throw Down (Part of) the Gauntlet.

5. Novalia Spirit:
-All Bugfixes except Remote Control are useful, this is included in a later patch that 
 fixes more things.
-Cursor-focused patches will cause problems within the attack menu.
-Sorting Fix is unneeded.
-Vanishing Magicite and Naming Shadow run into already existing text fixes.

6. Dijibriel:
-Rushing Celes Fix
-Wild Cat Fix

7. Imzogelmo:
-Carve Stone
-M-Tek Vehicle in Cyan's Soul event
-Mine Cart Fix isn't needed; it's already installed on TWUE
-Vector's Cure-Castin' Kid no longer heals the dead
-Gogo and the Cursed Shield.

8. mblock129:
-All bugfixes should work, including the little animation fixes.
-Using Edgar Revealed is not a good idea.

9. Remove the header.

10. Lenophis:
-Can't Lose For Winning
-Fancy Walking
-Anchor's Aweigh!

11. Leet Sketcher (Note: These are in no particular order unless otherwise mentioned. Remember 
  to check the readme included with each patch for which ones to use on your setup and keep in 
  mind what you've already applied, there's a reason why these are listed so late!)
-Just about everything works in the bugfix section of things, provided you saved these patches for last.
-Rule of thumb: if there's a patch listed in the readme as 'fix patch for a non-headered SNES ROM 
 with _______'s "_______" patch applied' and you've used the listed patch, use it instead of the regular 
 one.  Stuff will break if you don't.
-In order to use Dead Hare, you must first apply the reverse patch for Item/Magic Counter. Then apply Dead Hare,
 then reapply Item/Magic Counter. 
-Beware of Bye Bye Breath if you plan on doing any editing later.
-Imp's Retort is more or less the "second half" of Psycho Cyan.  You should probably be applying this if 
 you used that.
-Do NOT apply Side Saddle at all.  Magitek Madness is already applied and SS is contained in this one.
-Self Sneeze contains Remote Control, so you won't ever need that fix.
-It may be smarter to go with Soul Saved version A given what we're doing with a whole bunch of patches.

12.  Also some smaller tweaks like the SwdTech gauge speedup would go here if you feel it is warranted.

Do NOT use:
-Multi-Steal Fix will screw up some names.
-Zozo Sign Petty Fix was not meant for the uncensored ones, and therefore it will not look very good.
-Brushless Sketch is known to conflict with other patches.
-As a general rule, any and all fixes about dialogue and other text (description fixes, missing stuff 
 due to bugs, etc.) have already been dealt with by TWUE and then some.  They will overwrite these changes 
 and cause problems.  This includes patches that introduce new text.
-Open Eyes Terra currently has a bug that needs to be fixed before applying. 
-The standard Music Player patch does not work as it overwrites code and causes an issue. If wanted, use
the patch with add-ons. 
-King's Robes and Color Wheel seem to give a patching error. They are not recommended currently. 


Patches that are kind of iffy, and either require additional work or great care when applying:
-Shadow Status has compatibility issues with soft locking on the Floating Continent.
-Holy Randomness, Batman will overwrite some data found in the original patch.  Using it is not advised.
-The Multi-Font Selection patch would only work with a custom build of it; It won't work properly with the
 current version due to font changes.
-The restoration of the button config doesn't jive very well with TWUE Music Player Config 2.
 It works, but the Music Player's place on the menu gets taken up by the Button Config function.
-The restoration of SwdTech Renaming screws with the new Bushido names and will not work unless it can be
 customized to do so. 
-Randomosity Monster Random Encounter fix seems to slow down gameplay and if not patched properly can cause
softlocking of game upon play-testing. 